when you first go to design a workout
program whether it's for yourself or
you're work with an athlete or client
one of the most important things you
have to figure out is what are you going
to focus on there's so many different
things and goals and adaptations one
could be training or exercising or
working out for how do you know what to
do well if you don't have a very
specific plan in place you're going to
end up doing a little bit of this and
that and you're going to waste time
you're going to spend 17 hours writing
workout programs and oh you forgot this
and nothing will actually ever get
accomplished so in this episode of
55-minute
physiology what I want to do is take you
through my process of how I identify
what I'm going to train for this could
be again for my own self or for an
athlete or a client I'm working with
right anyone who's ever done any program
design or you know design workouts is
going to tell you this is a cyclical
process so step number one is what we
call a needs analysis and that's really
the focus of today's talk I'll show you
my system for how I analyze the needs of
a particular athlete or a
client after I do that then I'll show
you how I like to decide on the program
goals now sometimes this is already
decided for you so an athlete may show
up or a client and say hey I'm here
working with you because I specifically
need this okay so that's a little bit
different so sometimes they'll show up
and I need to get better at my sport you
tell me what I need to train for okay
great but sometimes they may say no I
need speed or I need strength or I need
muscle mass well sometimes they're right
and sometimes they're wrong in the
process of this video I'll show you how
that can occur and then some solutions
for that right and how actually you can
do it you'll make it easier for you to
get athlete Buy in but regardless after
you've identified that goals then you go
on with stuff that we've talked about in
many other videos which would be you
write the program and you adjust what
are called the modifiable variables so
this is what this acronym coover verb is
it's seven of them uh you know which
exercise to choose which order to do
them in how much volume how much
frequency how much exposure things like
that if you do that properly you will
get that adaptation you're looking for
or the client or the athletes looking
for and then hopefully a resulting
change in performance all right then if
you're a good coach you of course will
go back to the beginning right and so
we're constantly analyzing and adapting
right this worked this didn't work we
got a little bit better here but not
enough we already got plenty here so
let's focus more on
that if you're on social media probably
are
obviously you're going to and you and
you follow people in this field you
realize how complicated this stuff is
because it's information overload right
it's like well I need to be training for
this and that and that and that you're
like oh my God I'm just I don't know
what to do well hopefully again this
process will help you triage it's really
more of an algorithm to say okay yeah
all these things are important but
what's most important or what I really
need to get for that particular goal so
let's jump into this fine addition to
our 55 minute physiology lecture
series now to first off think I like to
focus how I teach my classes and and how
I think about training as there being
six basic adaptations to physical
training now there's infinite ones it
just depends on how you want to split
them up but that's not the point here
you can see them how I have them listed
skill is the first one all right this is
like a motor skill or motor control this
could be anything from shooting a
billiard ball better a basketball better
it could be running technique could be
squatting technique whatever mechanics
right so it's a skill development issue
then number 234 and five are actual
metrics I so did you get actually faster
can you move your body more powerfully
are you stronger hypertrophy did you add
muscle mass and then conditioning is
number six or endurance now in other
videos when I get more complicated I
actually split conditioning endurance up
into like 10 different types of
endurance conditioning same thing with
power and strength and all that stuff
but for now this is just the big
overview
right so I have those six things that I
can work on uh you could lump mobility
and flexibility in here anywhere you'd
like as things you have to have to be
able to do these things correctly but
again just think of the six that I put
out here so how do I actually know what
to train for in other words which of
these six do I pick when I have a new
client or athlete or I'm trying to
figure out what to do
myself well this is the system I like
step number one is you have to Define
your goal again in the two scenarios
I've already mentioned maybe this is
already defined for you or you don't
know right so you can sit down and you
can watch other videos and other
people's stuff to figure out how to set
goals and you can look up the acronym
smart and talk to sport psychologists
about goal setting and stuff that's not
really what I'm talking about here but
for whatever reason you've decided and
you set that Big Goal but then what I
like to do is is Step number two which
is identify the
defender what is defending you from that
goal sometimes it is synonymous with the
goal in other words some times the
reason you're here to get faster is
because you're actually just not fast
but other times it's not so the reason
you're not fast might not be a speed
issue it might be a movement technique
issue might be an injury issue might be
a body mass issue might be a strength
issue we don't know and that's what
there that's what the needs analysis is
really about is you're going to do
testing to figure out okay I know you
want to get a but what's actually really
stopping you from getting there then
once you do that you set appropriate
mini goals so this this is my super lame
joke that I tell to my students and I
show them and uh any of them that are
watching this right now they're going to
roll their eyes you're probably going to
do the same thing you'll be like Andy
that wasn't funny at all but I don't
care I'm going to do this all right so
prepared you're braced for a not funny
funny joke this is a picture of Hope
Solo she's awesome number one because
I'm from the Pacific Northwest so I love
all things Washington Hope was a Goldie
for University of Washington soccer team
and of course was on our national team
forever but can you see what I'm trying
to portray in the photo so behind hope
is the goal and what's hope doing she's
defending the
goal get
it
no all right my point being that's
really what this this talk and this
lecture is about is how do you identify
what those appropriate and specific
Defenders are so I'll give you one
example say the Big Goal has been
identified is you want to maximize
performance at a national high jumping
Championship okay fine no problem maybe
then through your testing and and
analytics you've decided that there are
three things that are actually stopping
an athlete from jumping higher maybe
they pull their hamstring constantly so
because of this they can't do enough
training to actually get faster or more
powerful or jump better or improve their
technique because they're always hurt
right so maybe they have everything you
just got to keep them able to handle the
training volume or maybe they've got too
much body fat all right if I'm fat I
can't go up it's hard and or maybe I
have low absolute strength now just
because you increase your squat strength
by 10 lbs doesn't necessarily mean you
jump higher but if you have poor leg
strength that it could be that fact
right and so then you would go through
each one of these Defenders and set a
very specific tangible and measurable
mini goal so for the ham the ham the
constant hamstring poles you might come
back and say okay in order to stop that
from happening we need to improve
hamstring flexibility by
15% now don't worry I know that that's
not what you would probably really do
for a constant hamstring pull you'd
probably look at mechanics and glute
activation a thousand other things but
just think of this at the conceptual
level right my point is you're
addressing the hamstrings very
specifically and you set some kind of
goal that says we want to improve this
by this metric to identify or fix that
defender of my hamstring
pulse for the body fat you want to
reduce body fat by say 8% or 3% or
whatever who cares and then for the leg
strength you want to improve your Squat
and deadlift by 20% I know these again
these numbers are unrealistic most most
of the time but you know hopefully
you're seeing the point so then that's
what I would do right and I would come
back and I would say okay this is what
you want this is what stopping you from
getting what you want now let's set
little goals to knock that down and it's
actually pretty simple then gives the
athlete a ton of relief the parent or
the other coaches a ton of relief
because you have a very specific plan to
attack what's stopping them from getting
what they want and everybody loves that
this is very very good and helpful for
athlete buyin
so how do you actually identify these
Defenders I'm going to walk you through
in this next middle section here some of
the tests and protocols I like to do or
at least a Scaffolding in which I happen
to think about my testing when an
athlete comes in and I've ENT trying to
identify those
Defenders so this is our quote unquote
needs analysis or or our
testing I like to break my needs
analysis section up into two specific
sections those that are relevant to the
sport the activity or the athlete and so
imagine I've got five or six MMA
fighters in I will look at things that
are that are very specific to the sport
of MMA so all of those Fighters are
going to have the same basic criteria
because they're all doing the same basic
sport but then the individual the
athlete one is specific to the person
all right so all six of them will maybe
have a different composition there this
is also very helpful if you're a high
school coach or someone who's actually
working with multiple Sports at a time
you still want to have a basic
Scaffolding in your head or actually in
your computer or in your office on paper
of what are the actual unique demands of
those basic sports right and then the
individualized tailoring of the program
goes in the athlet section so I've got
five from the sport listed here and 10
from the athlete one thing caveat will
give you here is is don't just follow my
numbers here uh make up your own go to
clinics read papers talk to other
coaches take some off this list you
don't like and other ways to do it
better the actual details here aren't
the important thing it's just the idea
that we're taking this type of approach
to analyze what our athletes actually
need and and how to address that all
right so if you disagree with one of
these things on my list fantastic I
would love to to hear more about
that okay so let's jump into them one by
one so that you can understand what I'm
talking about so let's start with the
sport
perspective all right so from the sport
number one was Energy System so let's go
into that a common mistake people make
here in fact I argue sometimes I think
having a little bit of exercise
physiology knowledge uh regarding Energy
Systems does coaches worse than it does
good right sometimes it's very harmful
and that's because it confus the
movement with the duration of the game
in other words you have a soccer player
and they play a 45 minute half don't go
back to your exercise physiology
textbook and look up what are the energy
systems for 45 minute workouts because
that's not actually what they're doing
you need to pay attention to what are
the movements being done or what are the
duration of movements so in the case of
soccer well this is different from a for
a midfielder versus a Defender versus a
goalie and so you need to look at well
okay uh my my athlete who's in this
position is doing 10 to 15 second Max
Speed bursts with typically uh 20 to 30
second active recovery and I have to do
that 40 times in a row per half or
something like that right whatever
happens to be so I can give you an
example for MMA that's what I work with
a lot in grappling you typically see
about 20 to second or so exchanges of
maximal effort followed by about 20 or
30 seconds of active kind of rest now if
you're in high school or college or
Olympic wrestling well that's a little
different if you're in Greco wrestling
it's a little different you get Judo
slightly different all these Sports have
their subtle nuances but in general the
grappling sports are about 20 to Second
exchanges or so where it's they're
broken pretty hard followed by about
that equal time of rest it's about a 1
to1 work rest ratio but in boxing or
striking Sports the the work to rest
ratio is more like 3 to 5 Seconds
followed by 15 or 20 seconds of recovery
right if you see like a four or five
punch combination in a fight that's only
that's less than a
second right A A 10sec striking exchange
would be dozens if not 50 60 70 strikes
that'd be a huge amount so you don't
really see that most striking sports are
one or two or three maybe four strikes
in a row would be a large combination
that's under one second and then they're
going to kind of actively rest move
around faint kind of move do these
things for another 10 or 15
seconds so I don't care that my Fighter
fights five five minute rounds per se I
care what are you actually doing what's
the style of your opponent so if I'm I'm
I have an athlete who's going to compete
against a wrestler well I'm going to
test and work a very different Energy
System than I am if they're going to
compete in a boxing match right because
I know I don't need you to be able to
say go all
out for 35 45 seconds per se if you're
going to go in a kickboxing fight or in
a movie Tie fight right or the opposite
if you're doing a grappling thing and so
pay attention to the movement duration
of the of the sport not the rules the
length of the quarters any of that type
of stuff in the game it doesn't
necessarily matter the best example I
can give you is
baseball right a baseball game takes
four hours but the actual demands of
movement within the in baseball are you
know a 10-second Sprint every 40 or 50
minutes basically so it's very very
different so don't get fooled up on that
but we do want to have a good depiction
understanding what are the energy
systems of the sport now if you're
working with a person who's not in a
sport per se just think about what are
the energy systems that they use during
their activity so are they working out
are they hiking what are they doing
physically most often or often times and
that's going to dictate the energy
systems are they doing cycle spin class
are they doing cardio kickboxing class
are they walking their dog what is it
they're doing and what are the movement
frequencies what the work to rest what
are the intervals and how long are those
intervals number two here performance
variables I've given you one example
let's say we take the sport of tennis
and what we would want to do is think of
what are all the performance variables
that are associated needed to be
successful in the sport of tennis I've
given you four here there are probably
many many other ones not the point when
you go to do this on your own I would
again encourage you to think of as many
as possible and so you want to do two
things number one figure out what are
all the things that are important number
two how relatively important are each
one of those things so in this example
look at agility that's the biggest
bubble because agility is incredibly
important for tennis performance so is
anerobic capacity aerobic capacity is
but that's a little bit more and then
look at grip strength okay that's
probably kind of important but if you
spent as much time training your grip as
you did agility with a tennis player
you're probably going to lose your job
pretty fast so it's going to be a minor
point that bubble's going to be very
very small if we compare this exact same
thing to say arm wrestling you see how
those bubbles change I don't know if
your aerobic capacity is that important
for an arm wrestler but grip strength is
probably pretty damn important all right
so again we're not only listing which
ones are
important but how relatively important
and then what other ones are there right
so there's surely some that are
important for tennis that we would take
off the list for arm wrestling and vice
versa right so don't just put these four
up here and move them you you got to
think through this stuff a little
bit number three is what I call
Performance versus skill so identify how
far down that performance versus skill
spectrum is the sport take something
like golf anything that you can do while
smoking a cigar and drinking 18 beers
and still be pretty good at a k ONN
daily it's not very performance-based to
me that's that's almost exclusively a
skill sport and it is an extremely high
skill sport Bo okay basketball is a
little in between so there's a huge
skill component to it with dribbling and
shooting but there's also a Major
Performance component to it you know
jumping speed sprinting speed change of
Direction Agility Physical performance
is very high and then going further down
the Spectrum something like powerlifting
I mean I know there's technique involved
with the deadlift Etc but let's be real
it's basically a strength movement right
there's not a tremendous amount of of
neuromuscular skill relative to
basketball and certainly not relative to
a pool or golf or throwing darts or
something like that so that's going to
help me understand how much time do I
need to spend in the weight room lifting
weights versus being on the sport or or
doing sport similar movements and things
like that again will help me triage to
understand what really to train for and
that's the goal of this
video next is the movement patterns I've
given you some examples right is is a
shoulder flexion extension is A sagittal
plane frontal plane use your bom
mechanics use your Kinesiology here is a
triple extension uh which is something
maybe some people have not heard of
triple extension is often referred to
when you extend the hip knee and Ankle
right so this is happens when you do
everything from jumping to sprinting to
even turning and rotating right because
you're extending all three of those
joints simultaneously a snatch uh it's
extremely common probably the most
common Global movement pattern in all
the sport is that triple extension so an
important
term uh to know and understand is why I
have a highlight in yellow right but
what other stuff again think about the
activities or the sport that are common
things that are uh movement patterns
that are associated with hockey are just
going to be very very different than
those things in rugby all right so go
through your brain and think through
your biomechanics class and identify
those general movement
patterns and then lastly here we're
going to look at common non- trauma
injury locations so I can't do anything
about one of my Fighters getting kicked
in the head not not not part of my
equation but I can do things about I
strain my hamstring running or I took a
step and I and I blew my ailles out
right or my I woke up today my shoulder
is just achy right so non- trauma
induced injuries and I bring up this
picture here anyone that's ever watched
soccer uh this drives me nuts right a
little tap on the shoulder and looks
like they've just you know broken their
collar bone in half and then two seconds
later they're playing just fine all
right so we're not talking about acute
trauma we're talking about overuse
strains and pols right so if we look at
a sport of golf per se probably the area
you'd focus on a lot is the low back
right because of all the twist twisting
and torsion going on especially if we
have bad abdominal and bad glute uh
activation going on or proper mechanics
you get a lot of low back strains there
so you would definitely want to make
sure if you're working with a golfer
you're addressing that area right making
sure that's something you look for that
might be slightly different than tennis
right we're talking tennis elbow is a
big thing and low back of course and
that again would be also very different
from someone like hockey where you'd be
really concerned with the adductors
because they're on the ice and the legs
are splitting out and so they get tons
of groin poles and overuse injuries um I
don't know a lot of golfers who are
pulling groins consistently anyways so
again you'd be able to say okay I'm not
that I'm not concerned about a groin of
a golfer but of all the things I have to
train
for it's just too far down the list I
need to make sure we test and and
monitor the low back movement quality or
whatever you're going to do again as
I've said before and this the last time
I'll say I promise it's not that any of
these other things aren't important it's
just with the limited amount of time you
have with an athlete especially if
you're talking about a professional
athlete or a college athlete that has
NCAA restrictions or a general client
but time is always a limiting factor and
so you got to be able to say look I know
that's important perhaps but we got to
really focus on the bigger thing that
Big Goal we've identified that's what
we're after and while we're on that note
again this is why I make them go through
that process we all are clear what the
damn big goal is and then what those
many goals are everything else is a
distraction potentially if you have more
time and you're more interested we can
add more things but we're not going to
cut out that big goal and get distracted
with something else if time is the
issue so those are several things from
the sport or activity perspective that I
consider with my needs analysis let's go
to the individualized section the
athlete so step number one body
composition and body mass depending on
who I'm working with if it's an it's an
athlete who's extremely lean already I
might just not even put this in the
equation if it's a football player like
Vernon Davis Vernon I I was fortunate
enough to work with when he was training
NFL combine you know 10 years or 15
years ago or whatever he was already
walking in looking sculpted body
composition was just not important so he
didn't waste time adding that to his
metric because he might have gone from
9% to eight or something and who cares
it didn't matter he all he performed
well he looked good didn't matter saved
time we cut it out at the exact same
time though a guy named Marcus hains was
training and Marcus was a little bit
different he played quarterback at
Virginia and so he was probably 220 LBS
or something like that but he was going
to have to play wide receiver or wanted
to play wide receiver in the NFL well he
wasn't necessarily the leanest guy we've
ever seen he was simply overweight I
don't exactly remember what his body
composition was but this was actually
turned in be body comp was one of the if
not the most important thing for several
reasons number one physically had to
look the part right part of the NFL
draft says you have to look a certain
way they they look at you with your
shirt off and they uh inspect you and
stuff and if you just look kind of
sloppy or over fat and you want to be a
skill position guy it just wasn't going
to work so that had to be major part of
the deal in addition he was a fast
athletic guy but he wasn't super fast I
think he was something like a 47 and
change kind of 40 guy which is not
tremendously fast for an NFL receiver
well we knew if we could just take 10 or
15 pounds of body fat off of him that
alone would be like running a 40- yard
dash without a 10 PB or 15lb
veston so if we could cut two t off his
or three t0 off his 40 yard dash time by
simply making him uh improving his body
composition that could be millions of
dollars that's in fact that that's
exactly what did happen we were able to
see pretty large improvements in his
vertical jump and 40 yard dash far more
than any other athlete not because he
did more speed work or anything like
that but simply because he took that big
old vest off basically so he ended up
getting drafted I think in the seventh
round or late round guy uh spent some
time with the St Louis Rams had a three
or four year career something like that
made several million dollars and I think
is on NFL pension so for him body
composition was extremely important
right so that's something you might
consider with your athlete do it matter
for you does it not matter for you
another example of something like
aerobic capacity so uh about 10 years
ago I went through every piece of
literature ever published on any combat
sport athlete this was uh 17 or 1800
studies and I plotted this graph and
what this shows you is combat sport
performance so how well they did they
they win more fights yes or no if they
won more fights this would be high
they'd go higher up that list vertically
and I plotted that against their V2 Max
and what you can see there pretty
clearly around 40 to 45 milliters per
kilog gram body weight per minute if
they improve their V2 Max they won more
fights but after they got past 55 or so
milliliters per kilogram per minute
improving their V2 Max further didn't
mean they want any more fights so this
is very common for many sports there's
kind of a minimal amount of aerobic
fitness you have to have but going from
good to great didn't improve them
anymore and so if I have an athlete that
comes in and I suspect or I know they're
in the middle the kind of bottom of that
V2 Max I might do a V2 Max test on them
and so we can track progress there I
want to see how bad they are
but if I know they're already super fit
they're one of my guys that are like
Patrick cumins that are 60 plus all the
time I I don't very to Max Tes him very
often for the max member anyways because
I know he's going to be super high up
there now I know the UFC performance
Institute has done this uh recently and
I think they've released their data um
it was funny as I mentioned it's about
15 years after I did this but it
actually lines up pretty well with with
what I found so this is actually from
their actual Fighters so that's really
cool uh I've actually had some athletes
before that have come in when they're
super overweight or out of shape and
they want to get a db2 Max test done and
I'm like there's no point uh but they
push so we do it and they end up being
35 or 40 and I'm like well you're not in
shape this doesn't really matter right
and so again this is how we can save
time of what are we deciding what to
test for what to train for what not to
test for in the case of someone who
shows up unfit a fighter anyways I'm not
going to go have them work on their V2
Max they if they haven't trained
anything in 3 months like you just need
to get back to training and then come
back and and we'll see
right anerobic capacity would be a
similar thing now anerobic capacity is
not your ability to jump high it's not
your maximum strength we're talking
about your maximal Anor robic capacity
so how much work can you do in say 30
seconds to two or three minutes of of
all out work right this is your interval
kind of stuff you know what's that
maximum number look like well if I had
something like a table tennis player I'm
probably not super super concerned with
their aerobic capacity maybe a little
bit
right but I don't know what the average
exchange is in a table tennis or ping
pong match but they're not doing
something all out for 45 seconds um it's
probably much shorter compare that to
something like a
crossfit well they might right this is
is actually super important to them so
their an maximal anerobic capacity
something that you get from like a
Windgate test if you're familiar with
that that would be something I'd be
concerned with so depending on your
sport or activity MMA is a good example
I'm very much concerned with that number
hockey is a good example we test the
Anaheim Ducks very regularly with this
NFL players we want to see what they're
at with this metrics we very rarely test
maximal aerobic capacity with a hockey
player we would um for other reasons but
the maximum number not
often kind of going further down that
line of conditioning um or or muscle
stuff looking at other things like
muscle performance so who knows right
could be agility 510 F test vertical
jump max strength Max reps whatever it
is you feel like from a muscle
performance you need to get information
on uh you would look out for that
individual athlete so again you can
imagine you have a we actually had this
one actually in the same uh time we were
working with Vernon there was an old NFL
vet offensive lineman there or a
fullback early sorry Mike played played
for the Saints for a long time uh all
the combine guys are working on their
225 test right so in the NFL combine
they have to do as many reps as they can
at 225 pounds so we train that prior the
combine and Mike came in one day and
just did like 40 in front of them just
to sort of show them he was better than
them or whatever but someone like Mike
he was never a part of his pre or post
testing because I knew even not training
for it you know years AG by he's already
bench his and that was never going to be
his limiting factor in his football
performance so he did other stuff like
his 5105 and vertical jump and things
but the 225 test was never a part of his
equation athletes that are weaker maybe
that is a part of their
equation and then also things like
injury history right if you have an
athlete who's been around like Cal
Ripken Jr like Russell Wilson who have
you know breaking records in the NFL or
breaking records in Major League
Baseball for uh consecutive starts or
games played Without missing a game I
think Cal Ripken played over 2,000
consecutive baseball games that's 160
baseball games this a year I mean you do
the math there right 12 13 14 something
like that years without missing a single
basketball game or baseball game never
rolled an ankle one time never got a
cold or a flute I mean that's insane I'm
probably not going to waste a tremendous
amount of time on injury screening I'm
not going to FMS Cal Ripken every month
he obviously he doesn't get injured I'm
not saying I'm just going to completely
let that go but I'm just not going to
occupy a huge amount of his time
contrast that was somebody like Ken
Griffey Jr who missed I don't know a
third of his of his major league
baseball career with injury hamstring PS
constantly he's also notorious for not
working out not wanting to to do a lot
of of strength conditioning well someone
like that I'm going to spend a
tremendous amount of time on movement
quality and and muscle activation things
like that because that is important
right so again this is how we triage
between people of what we're going to do
so that's the stuff from the perspective
of the sport and the perspective of the
athlete so now what I want to do is talk
about the testing order and so basically
the guidelines are this is very similar
to one of my other videos basically on
exercise order you can go watch
anthropometrics is just height weight
you know limb lengths things like that
uh but basically what you're going to do
is the non- fatiguing stuff all the way
down to the aerobic capacity I'm not
going to walk you through this entire
list but you should stop and hit pause
and take a look at all this right uh you
you can see you're can to do speed power
speed stuff first then power testing
then strength and then your conditioning
stuff at the end now I wouldn't do all
these in the same day that'd be way too
much so You' probably split this testing
if you want to do this many things over
multiple days just make sure you don't
violate the exercise order within the
same day so this could be maybe you've
decided to do two days of total testing
day one you do uh an agility test and
then a vertical jump test and then a
strength test and then a wind gate then
day two you do uh another different type
of agility test and then a medicine ball
throw for power a different strength
movement and then that's when you do
your V2 Max you know something like that
right so you can mix them up that way
you don't have to follow order within
multiple days but just within those
individual days don't do your VO2 max
test before before you go do your max
back squat test right or before you do
your 40 yard dash test that wouldn't
make any sense you'd get poor
results so once we've done all that and
we've collected our information how do I
know what to actually train for or to or
what goal to actually pick well let's go
back to
these six different
adaptations well to me the first thing
you have to do is identify and
understand the said principle that
stands for specific adaptation to
imposed demand what this basically means
is the best thing you could ever do to
get better at shooting free throws is
shoot free throws right the the
adaptation you get is specific to the
demand you place so if you place a
demand on the hamstrings to contract
with more maximal strength that's what
they'll do and so the best way to
improve the maximal strength of your
hamstrings is to do maximum or close to
maximum things that require hamstrings
to contract so that's first you identif
very specific problem make sure that you
are doing something very specific with
that muscle group or that action or that
energy system or whatever it is you're
going after right the adaptation is
specific as all that means so if we look
at this again what typically drives
adaptations in these areas for skill it
is practice right you have to do the
thing a lot you've heard the 10,000 reps
thing okay the concept is true right it
just takes a lot of practice for Speed
just make sure you're doing something
that is light and fast for power it's a
little bit heavier but still kind of
fast kind of moving in a different range
for strength it has to be something
heavy for hypertrophy it's kind of heavy
but you got to do a lot of volume and
then conditioning something to get you
tired if you do that you're probably
going to move them a lot closer towards
those individual goals or whichever one
you're working
on couple other things what about fat
loss now I handled this in any of my
physiology of fat loss videos but
basically this is going to be driven
from somewhere down the this end of the
Spectrum hypertrophy conditioning a
little bit of strength work is what you
would do to select or what you would
select if if you've identified fat loss
as the primary goal of course nutrition
plays a much bigger part but you know
programming wise this is what you would
do what about rehab or prehab right what
if it's an injury issue well that could
come from any one of these areas so
maybe you have to rehab a hamstring by
getting it stronger or maybe it is a
skill maybe you're not firing or
sequencing properly so that'd be a issue
maybe the reason your shoulder hurts is
because one of your traps is smaller
right or off whatever right it could be
a hyper fish you just need to get bigger
rhomboids right they're weak and they're
small or it could be the reason you're
having this movement pattern dysfunction
is fatigue right so maybe you move
really well until you get tired and you
break down you lose flexion in your back
and now that's why your low back starts
to hurt right or in the case of the
golfer maybe they're fine in the first
tea but as they get more fatigued at the
end of the round they start letting
their abs off and glutes off they lose
the acquisition that's why they get
tired right so skill won't necessarily
help that that's a conditioning issue
it's conditioning of the skill my point
being again why are you not moving well
or why are you moving improperly is
there strength issue activation skill
etc etc and fix it that way for General
Health someone just comes to you and
says I want to get
healthier well that could be anything
right all of those different training
adaptations play a critical role in
overall human
health now that You' figured out what to
train for the Defenders you've gone to
the needs analysis just a little bit at
the end here about what type of workouts
to actually do now before I get going
any further I have covered this stuff
all pretty extensively in other videos
so check it out on my YouTube page or my
patreon account ww.
patreon.com Andy Galpin
uh all these videos are up on that uh
these are in a combination of 5 minute
25 minute and 55 minute physiology
videos so enjoy the rest of those
particularly the exercise Choice video
but the big concept here is the methods
are many and the concepts are few and
lots of people have said this before in
different combinations of words but this
is really what we're getting at right so
my point is you've identified you need
to get more
powerful don't worry about the very
specific methods because those are
infinite just hit the concept so as long
as you're hitting those appropriate
ideas the methods are really really
really infinite
right and that's because programming is
both an art and a science we've talked
about this uh you you've heard about
this in infinite areas of life but the
scientific
side is the concept the art is the
methods right so here in other videos
I've outlined where the scientific
concepts of power training where the
scientific Concepts Etc how many reps
should I do what's the weight what are
the things I need to do to make sure I'm
training to be more powerful I think I
have this in a big 55 minute video
actually and several the artistic side
is well did you like to use a kettle
bell versus a dumbbell or did you like
to use a band or did you like to use
post activation potentiation or contrast
that's more of an art thing and less of
a science I'm not saying there isn't any
science to it I'm just saying it's less
so it's more important to make sure
you're doing the things like I pointed
out earlier for power got to be kind of
heavy and fast for Speed got to be fast
so make sure that the athletes moving
fast you're probably going to get faster
you play with the methods right so the
example I like to give here is the
chromatic scale so I'm not musically
talented at all Natasha my wife is
hopefully some of you are but apparently
there are 12 scales in the chromatic
scale so in the history of all music for
the most part it's all come from
different combinations of those same 12
Concepts right and so someone
who makes a sound like this is using
exact same 12 methods or some same tool
of Concepts but applying in a different
method than someone like
krs1 and he's doing it someone
differently than someone like Pearl Jam
so we can get these contrasting
different sounds because the artistic
side of them is combining those same
Concepts differently it's all good
music but it's all very very different
right and so that's what I mean by using
the same concept the same 12 things but
use your artistic expression to make it
look different feel different perform
slightly
differently so what are some of those
scientific Concepts from a global scale
number one you will need to pick your
needs analysis of your sport items said
principle right specific adaptation and
imposed demand tell me what you need to
work on then go work on it number two
needs to be some sort of progressive
overload and so we have to have some
sort of balance between stress and
Recovery this is program design at its
real heart this is the difficulty of it
right so if I don't progress load or
intensity or reduce volume or if I don't
have some type of progression I'm not
going to continue to get any better but
if I progress too much like the third
point then I'm going to get hurt or then
I'll stop making progress right and so
we want to slightly this could be again
adding more repetitions it could be
adding more weight it could be adding
more complexity it could be reducing the
rest intervals who knows but something
has to progressively get better and and
these Concepts again are true no matter
which adaptation you're talking about so
the third one balance said and what I've
abbreviated is long-term athletic
development here this is a little bit
different than like developing a youth
athlete but my point is being this yes
the best way for you to ever get
stronger at your bench press is to do a
one rep max bench
theoretically but if all you did all day
was put on your max your 100% of your
Max and try to gift it up try to lift it
up that's your only training program
that's going to work for a short amount
of time but eventually that's going to
plateau and so you want to balance that
very specific training with
long-term progression so in the world of
program design or
periodization what we typically look
like is this the farther out from
competition you are the more of that LTA
the more very general stuff you do and
so you would do bench press sets of 10
15 you would build a base you would add
hypertrophy you do sets of five six
whatever you're going to do then as you
get closer and closer to competition you
get more and more and more specific
right but if you're too specific for too
long you get overuse injuries right the
the risk of that goes really high the
risk of plateau goes really high if you
don't do specific enough you don't
actually get enough imposed demand of
what you're actually needing and so we
want to balance that General and
specific and again typically way to do
that is to be very general farther out
from competition be more specific as you
get closer if there is no said
competition time what you would do is a
little bit of both right so do some very
specific work but then complement that
with some non-specific work so yeah do
your very heavy bench press but then
also on other days do push-up variations
do unilateral dumbbells uh multiple rep
ranges do different things like that of
course work your back all that stuff and
the last one is maximize adherence so
none of these Concepts matter your
program design doesn't matter at all if
your athlete doesn't do them if your
client can't stick to them consistency
matters most right so figure out well he
likes to do the heavy one or Max stuff
but hates doing the the volume work well
figure out how you can get them then the
example I give there is when I used to
train professional athletes
fulltime we'd have a hard time getting
them to show up on Saturday cuz we were
down in Phoenix so they always fly up to
Vegas for the weekend and they would
never show up to Saturday workouts and
Saturdays is is when we would do a lot
of the mobility a lot of Maintenance
work a lot of the non-sexy kind of
boring stuff and recovery and and
Chiropractic and all this stuff and and
they just won't show up for it and so we
had to incentivize them a little bit and
what we did is we said all right look
you know what Saturdays are gun show
days so you're going to show up Saturday
we're going to do a little bit of ABS
we're going to do all buys and tries and
we would go around the room if there's
10 guys sitting around be like okay you
pick your favorite bicep exercise you
pick yours and you pick one and you pick
your favorite try and you pick your
favorite try and pick your favorite try
I don't care what you do we didn't
program at all we let them do whatever
the hell they want but they didn't get
to do it until they finished their
maintenance
work and so we didn't tell them that
part we basically just said you show up
okay we do all this stuff first then we
do gun Showdown and our and our
adherence and our our participation
basically went to 100% everyone showed
up even if they went to Vegas they flew
back or hung over they showed up they
got their maintenance stuff in got
whatever things we needed to get worked
on and then they got to pump their own
right so it's something that we didn't
need them their biceps to be any bigger
getting ready for the NFL combine
especially guys like
Vernon
but that's what we had to do to drive it
adherence so that's a big Concept in
terms of the art that comes down to
things like your motivational tactics
the time of day you like to work out
again I mentioned the equipment do you
like bosu ball do you like kettle bells
you like
your periodization philosophy the time
of day etc etc etc I'm not saying this
stuff isn't important or it's not
scientific it is but that really comes
down of the art in the context the
situation who you're working with the
type of client what what do you have
access to what do you not have access to
uh you can get things done like you can
get almost the exact same thing done
with a Kell Bell that you can a dumbbell
very similar to a barbell and a lot of
aspects there's a huge crossover not the
same but there's a huge crossover is the
point all right so how do I know which
exact exercise to pick again check this
out and I actually have an exercise
selection exercise Choice video up
multiple of them so go check those out
but basically what we're talking about
is this right you did the needs analysis
and now you decided on the program
design and now we're going to that
modifiable variables that choice order
frequency and things like
that okay so to get into these
modifiable variables a little bit we'll
talk about this separately in other
material but there's seven of them the
choice order frequency progression
intensity volume and rest some people
have six some people have eight it
doesn't matter it's just helping you
think of them
conceptually but I want to test your
learning now so here you
go all right what I have is a list one
two 3 four and then a b c so which one
of these match the following I'll give
you a second to pause the
video all right so see if you can match
them oh and then I'll give you Hint by
the
way it's a trick question
right so if you've seen some of the
other videos you'd know that this isn't
necessarily true right so a bicep curl
in other words the exercise doesn't
necessarily determine the exact
adaptation it's the application of the
exercise so a bicep cural could be for
power if you did it powerfully it could
be for strength if you did it heavy it
could be for endurance if you did a lot
more repetitions so I will grant you
things like a snatch aren't particularly
good to use for hypertrophy and an ellip
itical isn't the best choice ever for
power but at the at the basic level any
exercise can be used for any adaptation
it's not the exercise per se it's the
application how fast did you do it how
many reps did you do it how heavy was it
right etc etc I've expanded on this
concept in other
videos but the big concept again
exercises do not determine adaptation
application determines
adaptation the exercises right the
application as I just mentioned speed
technique all that stuff determines it
um so I'll give you one example while
we're here just because I program a
squat doesn't mean you're going to be
using your hamstrings right if you're
using a wide squat or a more narrow
squat or you lean more forward or your
different anthropometrics that could be
really heavily using the hamstrings and
gluten it could be using the
quads right two people doing the exact
type just type of of squad you you
program front squats narrow stance front
squats well that doesn't necessarily
mean it's going to be a quad activator
it really depends on the person right
depends on their technique and are they
sitting back with their hips are they
driving straight down what are they
doing so the application how they
execute the exercise determines things
like which muscle is being used what
adaptation I kind of
get the exercises do determine several
things though the movement plane of
course right uh my sagittal frontal
transverse the muscles and the joints
being used generally the contraction
type is an isometric concent CC Ecentric
and then the technical proficiency is
that last one right
so uh giving giving an athlete an
exercise that they're not technically
proficient and it's going to change a
lot and determine a lot of the exercise
so what you get out of it all right so
another kind of a trick question here
just go along with me but I'm telling
you it's a trick okay on the top of the
screen you see cardio and then you have
strength and I'm going to flash you up
some pictures and I want you to tell me
which column it would go in I know the
obvious answer here
is depends on the application right but
let's just follow along and see so where
does that exercise go that's cardio
right perfect how about that one look at
Jason squatting heavy there that's a
strength
exercise what about jogging okay that's
cardio what about heavy lifting overhead
press look at Janny
go okay that's string well obviously
hopefully you're getting the feel of
what I'm talking about here but that's
false right I don't know what adaptation
you're going to get it depends on the
execution right and what we're actually
doing so a very good example that I got
from my friend Cal deeps so you can
listen to an episode on the Barbell
Shrugged podcast I did with cal um
episode 2117 but he is a legendary
strength conditioning coach at the
University of Minnesota has coached a
ton of national champions and uh other
world champions in track and field and
throwers and things like that
well on this podcast he described how he
said look I got 300 plus pound football
players and shot Putters I need them to
do some cardio but I can't have them go
jog for 30 minutes it's going to blow
their backs and knees to Pieces so he
does
cardio by having them do one repetition
at 50% of their bench then one
repetition at 50% of their Squat and
they just cycle back through that for 30
minutes so they get two things lined up
together they go one rep one rep one rep
and he can get the same exact cardio
workout done
without actually having to jog or swim
or cycle and so we really I want you to
really expand your mind and think about
that type of stuff as long as I'm
getting the concept continuously moving
for 30
minutes the other stuff is Art right you
like to jog you like to cycle you want
to set up a little circuit I know my
friend and colleague PJ nestler has done
this a lot with MMA fighters set up a
little circuit and you got to move
around they drag a sled and they maybe
push something throw some dumbbell or
throw some medicine balls uh PL LS and
you just kind of have a combination it's
all very low intensity it's not this
killer circuit it's just trying to get
them to move and not stop for 30 minutes
but not having these spiders jog um I
have a couple that do this but the vast
majority athletes I work with I
typically recommend we don't need a lot
of road work right if you want to get a
30 or 45 minute uh steady state exercise
in that's fine but I want to do
something a little bit different unless
you're very good and used to running
right so that's just another example of
they the exercise itself jogging doesn't
determine cardio or vice versa right we
could use anything to get there the
opposite in this spectrum people abuse
box jumps all the time I'm not against
box jumps but they think of this as a
power exercise I'm going to improve my
power I'm going to do box jumps okay
great jumping is a good way to improve
power oh but you're going to do 50 in a
row you can do a set of 100 you can do
the max amount of reps you can do in 5
minutes well it's not a power exercise
if you aren't jumping powerfully so if
you're doing a bunch of rep itions in a
row you have to reduce power output
because fatigue sets in and if you're
doing something submaximally how are you
getting better at maximum so if you're
using box jumps for conditioning cool if
you're using box jumps a whole bunch in
a row trying to get powerful you're
using the wrong exercise for the wrong
adaptation right remember it's not the
exercise a box jump alone doesn't make
you more powerful it's the application
the sets the Reps the intensity the
volume
so there's another good example of one
exercise that can be used for two
totally diametrically opposed
adaptations could be great for anerobic
conditioning if you do a bunch in a row
could be great for power if you do one
or two in a row as high as you possibly
can so it's the execution again that
matters
folks I've given other examples of these
two things so this is me doing this
funny goofy little exercise of one armed
kettle bell onelegged
single leg Squad on a BOS or on a
medicine ball and it's s right and so
when we're trying to figure out which
one of these exercises is better there's
a whole holist of things we want to uh
consider but those are outlined in the
exercise choice or outlined in the
exercise Choice
video so to wrap up when you do that
when you finalize this whole system the
last thing I do then is go through my
three-step system which is one identify
the goal we've covered that today then I
want to balance so I make sure that okay
I need to get my hamstring stronger okay
I can't just do hamstring strength I got
to make sure that I'm balanced so I got
to balance that by doing some quad work
and I got to balance the joint by doing
some adductor and abductor work right so
that I make sure that joint is stable
and moving correctly because I know the
hamstring is about to get loaded a
bunch or overhead pressing or bench
pressing the example I gave bench
pressing right so I want to make sure
I'm balancing the shoulder joint by
doing a bunch of or maybe even extra
pulling work right or rotational work
whatever happens to be right balancing
that system out
and then the third step is
individualized um so we can get there
with our exercise choice so you don't
like dumbbells you like okay Gray we can
individualize things a little bit better
um to get to wherever we want to get so
that's it hopefully you've learned a lot
about how to select which types of
things to train for when you've got a
new client or an athlete or even
yourself if you appreciated this uh I
would greatly appreciate your support
you can subscribe to this YouTube page
you can check out other videos on my
page page or my website Andy galpin.com
my patreon page I use all that money
actually I give that to students that's
the honest answer they help me make
these videos they help me organize this
stuff I got a bunch of new things coming
where I'm going to be creating notes for
these and summaries and guidelines uh
but I have to be able to make this
viable and these videos take me a
tremendous amount of time so anything
that you'd be able to contribute on
patreon would be fantastic you can sign
up there and find me there and
contribute a buck two to the videos and
I take that money give it to my students
or interns or volunteers and they're
able to create um some unique stuff
that's going to help you even more get
what you want of these videos so I
appreciate that support you can also
check me out on on all my social media
platforms Dr Dr Andy Galpin and yeah
until next
time get out there do something fun GO
train go do something you haven't done
in a long time try that right do
something that's not specific to your
goal
and do something different so good
training be strong see you later